Today's *דף* daf is *ס"ז* Samach-Zayin 67 and we pick up at
the top of *ס"ז* Samach-Zayin at the two dots. We just did
yesterday a major topic in *הלכה* Halakha which is the issue about
*ריחא*, Reicha, about taste transfer through smell, or the status of smell.
As we said, the question was to what degree when somebody ingests
smell through their nose or through their mouth as well, you know,
we spoke about how you also smell through your mouth, that's why
smell is part of the definition of *מינו* Mino or *אינו מינו*
Eino Mino which was part of the debate of *אביי* Abaye and
*רבא* Rava and how much if you ingest smell is that like
actually ingesting the object itself. We have a principle, one way of
saying it is *טעם כעיקר*, Ta'am k'Ikar, the taste of something is
like the thing itself, but to what degree do we say *ריחא
כעיקר*? Reicha k'Ikar?
So anyway, that was a major debate and between *אביי* Abaye and
*רבא* Rava and *רבא* Rava basically said that *ריחא לאו מילתא היא*,
Reicha lav miltha hi, *ריחא* Reicha is not meaningful, and there was
this *תוספות* Tosafot and we discussed that *תוספות* Tosafot works it out
because there's a similar debate in the *גמרא* Gemara in *פסחים* Pesachim
between *רב* Rav and *לוי* Levi about *ריחא מילתא* Reicha miltha and
there, based on the normal *כללי פסק* klalei pesak or whatever, the
conclusion would seem to be that *ריחא* Reicha is *מילתא*, miltha, is
a problem. So *רש"י* Rashi basically *פוסק* paskens like our *גמרא* Gemara
against that *גמרא* Gemara and says *ריחא לאו מילתא*. Reicha lav miltha.
*תוספות* Tosafot tries to reconcile all the *סוגיות* sugyot and try to
create some hierarchy and say that maybe there are some cases that
*ריחא* Reicha is *מילתא*. miltha. And the cases that *תוספות* Tosafot specifically
would say *ריחא* Reicha is *מילתא* miltha is when there's a very
condensed type of an oven if you're, well the thing I should
say is how does *ריחא* Reicha transfer? So the *גמרא* Gemara spoke
about either directly smelling something or putting a hot piece of bread
on top of a barrel of wine, but the *גמרא* Gemara there
talks about cooking things in near proximity. So *תוספות* Tosafot says that
even if we *פוסק* pasken *ריחא מילתא* Reicha miltha based on the
*גמרא* Gemara over there, that would only be when they're being cooked
in near proximity and in a very closed environment, meaning cooking two
things in the oven at the same time, uncovered *מילכיגס* milchigs and
*פליישיגס* fleishigs and there's just a lot of steam and so on
and therefore a lot of transfer. And *תוספות* Tosafot therefore that would
lead to a conclusion that that is a problem. You can't cook
uncovered *מילכיגס* milchigs and *פליישיגס* fleishigs in the oven at the same
time and I mentioned this yesterday and I just want to repeat
it, that that is the extent where *תוספות* Tosafot thinks there's an
issue. Like nowadays people have two ovens, maybe four ovens because of
*פסח* Pesach too, maybe six because you want one for *פרווה*, parve,
I don't know, but anyway but in *תוספות*, Tosafot, in *תוספות* Tosafot
there was no question that you could cook one after another even
*טרף* treif after *כשר* kosher you could cook, and the only question
was cooking them and no question you could cook them covered at
the same time, the only question was uncovered at the same time
and even there *תוספות* Tosafot says that because we have big ovens
and I would say now because we have ventilated ovens it's really
not an issue and *תוספות* Tosafot really allowed cooking *כשר* kosher and
non-kosher uncovered stuff at the same time, and the only degree to
which he had an issue was around *פסח* Pesach time because maybe
*ריחא* Reicha is not enough to be considered like there's the *טעם*
Ta'am of something, but maybe it's enough to be considered like there's
a *משהו*, Mashehu, and by *פסח* Pesach stuff that's actually baked on
*פסח* Pesach itself, there would be an *איסור משהו*. Issur Mashehu. So
that was the degree to which *תוספות* Tosafot had that issue. And
I should say that, you know, that nowadays to the degree that
*הלכה* Halakha there's a discussion of the status of ovens, people generally
follow *תוספות* Tosafot's lead. So why is there an issue at all
about ovens? So to the degree that there is, it's because the
*רא"ש* Rosh introduces a new concern, not *ריחא* Reicha but *זיעה*, Zeia,
which is the actual evaporated liquid, the condensation, yeah, condensation, steam,
and of course the irony is is that the *גמרא* Gemara didn't
pay attention to *זיעה* Zeia and if *זיעה* Zeia was an issue
why were the *גמרות* Gemaras only talking about *ריחא*? Reicha? Why weren't
they also talking about *זיעה*? Zeia? So there's some that reject the
*זיעה* Zeia concern as well, there's some that say even if *זיעה*
Zeia is a concern again in our larger ovens and ventilated ovens
etc. it's not an issue. And also if it's covered? If it's
covered it's certainly not an issue etc. etc. etc. They even used
communal ovens, like if you if you bake *טשולנט* cholent you'd go
to the bakery. Right, so thank you for that, yeah. One of
the reasons *תוספות* Tosafot also points out is he says that we
don't have an opportunity to even, you know, because we all are
using the same communal oven so we can't control the situation, which
has to do also with like affluence and how affluence and, you
know, affects sort of like *הלכה* Halakha or which types of *הלכתי*
halakhic concerns people, you know, want to pay attention to.
Like the fact that
now, the fact that now we have this huge *הכשר* Hechsher industry
means that we feel, oh you can't eat something until you have
a totally *מוכשר* hechshered and supervised everything. And if you go, you
know, *תוספות* Tosafot's time and even nowadays in Europe, you make certain
assumptions based on a general, you know, basic parameters of what the
assumed facts are. You don't assume and you don't go ahead and
say, oh I have to make sure that I can supervise everything,
if you're allowed to make certain assumptions. So the same actually is
true now. Now if we're affluent and have the money or a
lot of people are, why not have two ovens? But anyway, but
those are some of the issues there, yes. I've also met Jews
from North Africa who in the 20th century were cooking in the
same ovens with Muslims. There you go. Okay, so now let's continue.
We couldn't even worry about *בישול עכו"ם*. Bishul Akum. potentially. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, if they're cooking it or if they're whatever. Okay, let's take
it now we continue with that with a different משנה Mishnah then.
All right, all right, we're moving on, we're moving on, five lines
from the top, ס״ז ע״א. Samech Zayin Amud Aleph. We're going to
continue ס״ז Samech Zayin 67. We're going to continue with topics that
are extremely relevant for anybody learning כשרות. Kashrut. So we just did
ריחא Reicha and now we're going to continue. זה הכלל, Ze Haklal,
this is the principle, going back to the משנה. Mishnah. כל שבהנאתו
בנותן טעם, Kol shebehana'ato benoten ta'am,
anything that, again, the grammar is funny, "in its pleasure there is
taste." What it really means is בנתינת טעמו יש הנאה benetinat ta'amo
yesh hana'ah
is really what it's saying. In its giving of taste, the taste
actually gives, makes is a positive taste as opposed to טעם לפגם,
ta'am lifgam, a negative. In some interesting debate in the ראשונים, Rishonim,
let's say it's a neutral taste. We're going to assume that neutral
and positive are the same, that but if it's a negative taste,
if it makes the thing taste worse, then even though you can
taste it, it's not a problem. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הכי
הלכתא, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel Hachi Hilchata, that we rule that
way. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל לא שנו אלא שנפל לתוך גריסין
רותחין. Ve'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel Lo Shanu Ela Shenafal Letoch Grisin
Rotchin. The scenario in the משנה Mishnah where it's permissible that we
consider that this vinegar falling on this these types of grain is
a gives a bad taste, that's only if the grain was like,
you know, the oatmeal or whatever was hot. Okay, אבל נפל לתוך
גריסין צוננין, aval nafal letoch grisin tzonenin, but it fell onto cold
oatmeal, והרתיחן, ve'hirtichan, and then you cooked and then you heated it
up, okay, that case, נעשה כמי שהשביח ולבסוף פגם. na'aseh kemi she'hivshiach
ulevasof pagam. In that case,
it's like, תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean it's like? It
is! But anyway, that first it gave a positive taste. Apparently vinegar
with cold oatmeal tastes good. Grits. Grits, right. Grits, grits, maybe it's
oh, maybe. Anyway, the problem is only when it's heated up, then
it gives a slight off-taste. So here, if the initial mixture was
a positive taste, then when that non-kosher vinegar, the יין נסך Yayin
Nesech vinegar got mixed up, okay, the oatmeal became forbidden. It now
had a positive taste of a non-kosher food, and it became forbidden.
Now you heat it up and there's a slightly off-putting taste. Since
the oatmeal is still edible, it remains forbidden. Once it got a
status of forbidden, it remains forbidden. נעשה כמי שהשביח ולבסוף פגם ואסור,
na'aseh kemi she'hivshiach ulevasof pagam ve'asur, and
it remains forbidden. וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן לא שנו אלא שנפל לתוך גריסין רותחין. Vechen ki
ata Ravin amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan lo shanu
ela shenafal letoch grisin rotchin. It's only if the vinegar initially fell
into these hot grits. אבל נפל לתוך גריסין צוננין, aval nafal letoch
grisin tzonenin, but it fell into cold grits, והרתיחן, ve'hirtichan, and then
you heated it up, נעשה כמי שהשביח ולבסוף פגם ואסור. na'aseh kemi
she'hivshiach ulevasof pagam ve'asur. Then it's a case where it first gave
a positive taste and made it forbidden, and now the taste is
a negative one and it remains forbidden. וכן כי אתא רב דימי
וכולי, Vechen ki ata Rav Dimi vechulei, okay,
whoever was writing down the גמרא Gemara did not want to repeat
that whole thing a third time. I know. I know. וכך היו
עושים בערבי שבתות בציפורי. Vechach hayu osim be'arvei shabbatos beTzippori.
This is actually what they used to do in ציפורי Tzippori on
ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. This was a classic, I guess, שבת Shabbat
dish they would make. They would mix it up with cold grits
and קורין אותם שחליים, korin otam shachlayim, they'd call it שחליים. shachlayim.
Now I know like ציפורי Tzippori has any value is I think
is I think ציפורי Tzippori is the only town in Israel there's
uninterrupted Jewish presence.
Really?
Interesting. So that's why the ציפורי Tzippori maybe. Okay, interesting.
Now the question is did they mix it up just with cold?
Because why would they mix it up with cold and heat it
up if it tastes bad when it's heated up? So תוספות Tosafot
says they mixed it cold, heated it up, and then let it
cool down again. So when it was cold again, now it started
now now the off-taste was was no longer present. Whatever. אמר ריש
לקיש. נותן amar Reish Lakish noten. טעם לפגם tam lifgam. שאמרו,
when they say נותן טעם לפגם, noten ta'am lifgam, if it gives
a bad an off-putting taste it's permissible, לא שיאמרו קדירה זו חסרה
מלח יתירה מלח חסרה תבלין יתירה תבלין. lo she'yomru kedira zo chasera
melach yetira melach chasera tavlin yetira tavlin.
Not in the case where you say, now this is a חומרא,
chumra, okay, where you would say like, oh, the reason when we
added this vinegar it made this thing taste bad is only because
the the spices weren't correct to begin with. Like we had a
little too much salt or too little salt, too much, you know,
cinnamon, too little cinnamon. And if we had had the right amount
of spices, right, then it would have tasted good.
With this extra vinegar. So therefore let's consider the extra vinegar נותן
טעם לשבח noten ta'am leshevach because in an ideal circumstance it would
have improved it. So that's a חומרא. chumra. You're saying even though
whatever, right, even though I acknowledge that right now it made the
taste bad, since it was only due to the contributing factors of
the certain mix of spices and had the spices been properly mixed
it would have been good, we should consider it in theory to
be giving a good taste. Okay. So you could have done it
before, but let's say you can fix it afterwards. Like, you know,
in other words, with the vinegar. Okay, now we can add the
salt, it'll be good. Does that make a difference?
Let me not deal with your case for a minute. I got
to just get through this case. Hold on. לא שיאמרו קדירה זו.
lo she'yomru kedira zo. So don't say, oh, the only, you know,
so the אלא כל שאינה חסרה כלום ואינה אלא מפני זה. ela
kol she'eina chasera klum ve'eina ela mipnei zeh. I'm sorry, I think
I misexplained this again because it's I keep on getting it's like
a tricky way to explain this phrase. אלא, ela, let me just
finish it and then אלא כל שאינה. ela kol she'eina.
I'm sorry, this is I might have just said the second position.
This this is the מחמיר machmir position. מחמיר machmir position is
is
that is
that is that...
Okay, don't say
that the only, jeez,
one minute, third time.
Well,
let me say Rashi's way. I'm trying to read it Tosafot's way,
which is confusing me. The way Rashi reads it is the following.
Rashi reads it, at least it's easier to parse the words. Rashi
reads it the following way. He says, do, even if it has
a bad taste, don't try, don't say,
don't try to discount the bad taste. No, you are going to
discount. Oh my God, I keep on going to the second reading,
which is the מקיל mekil one. Something in me is preventing me
from reading it the מחמיר machmir way. Hold on. People can do
a good פירוש perush on that. Okay. לא שיאמרו קדירה זו חסרה
מלח יתירה מלח חסרה טעם יתירה תבלין אלא כל שאינה חסרה כלום
ואינה נאכלת מפני זה. lo sheyomru kedera zu chasera melach yesera melach
chasera tam yesera tavlin ella kol she'eina chasera klum v'eina ne'echeles mipnei
zeh. Already went to the second one.
Oh,
okay, fine. Right, right, right. Okay. So here's the point, okay. Don't
try to discount the פגם. pagam. Right? Is that right? As soon
as I think I have it, it goes away from me. לא
שיאמרו קדירה זו חסרה מלח יתירה מלח חסרה טעם יתירה תבלין אלא
כל שאינה חסרה כלום ואינה נאכלת מפני
זה. lo sheyomru kedera zu chasera melach yesera melach chasera tam yesera
tavlin ella kol she'eina chasera
klum v'eina ne'echeles mipnei zeh.
Okay, let's try the third time. I'm sorry I keep on getting
confused here. So the point is,
it is נותן טעם לפגם noten tam lifgam and you want to
say and he, what he's doing is he is limiting the cases
where נותן טעם לפגם noten tam lifgam is going to be מותר.
muttar. נותן, Noten, let me let me work backwards. נותן טעם לפגם
noten tam lifgam is only going to be מותר muttar if the,
if it's
clear that the פגם pagam comes from this additive. But if it
is possible that the פגם pagam is coming from some other reason,
like it is coming because the spices are a little off and
it's possible that that is the source of the פגם, pagam, then
you can't say that this thing, that it's the פגם pagam of
this thing which is the problem. Now that's what it's trying to
say. Let me see if I can read that into the words.
Let's try again.
לא שיאמרו קדירה זו חסרה מלח יתירה מלח חסרה טעם יתירה תבלין
lo sheyomru kedera zu chasera melach yesera melach chasera tam yesera tavlin
אלא כל שאינה חסרה כלום ואינה נאכלת מפני זה. ella kol she'eina
chasera klum v'eina ne'echeles mipnei zeh. The only type of פגם, pagam,
let's start from the last line, the only type of פגם pagam
that is מותר muttar is when it is clear that there's nothing
else that's off of from the pot and this is the only
thing making it taste bad. But if you're able to say, that's
what's tripping me up, לא שיאמרו lo sheyomru means if you not
in a case when you are able to say. If you are
able to say that part of the problem might be that the
spices are off, then you don't get to say נותן טעם לפגם.
noten tam lifgam. Okay, so let's read that again. One more time.
אמר ריש לקיש נותן טעם לפגם שאמרו לא שיאמרו Amar Reish Lakish
noten tam lifgam she'amru lo sheyomru is not in a case where
you are able to say that קדירה זו חסרה
מלח יתירה מלח חסרה טעם יתירה תבלין. kedera zu chasera melach yesera
melach chasera tam yesera tavlin. It does not apply in a case
where you're able to say that the spices are off. That's you're
not allowed to say נותן טעם לפגם noten tam lifgam because maybe
it has to do with the spices. אלא, Ella, no we gotta
get through this. כל שאין חסרה כלום, kol she'ein chasera klum, it
only applies to a case where it's clear that the spices are
right, ואינה נאכלת מפני זה, v'eina ne'echeles mipnei zeh, and it is
the פגם pagam that makes it bad tasting. Okay? So that version
of the explanation is you cannot say נותן טעם לפגם noten tam
lifgam if it might be based to a different mixture of the
spices, okay, or if
those or if the spices somehow in conjunction with this thing give
it a bad taste. That's not נותן טעם לפגם. noten tam lifgam.
נותן טעם לפגם noten tam lifgam is only when the spices are
perfect and it still gives טעם לפגם. ta’am lifgam Okay, that's that's
version one.
ואיכא דאמרי V'ika d'amri other say אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish.
נותן. Any time that you are at that, that saying
the spices are off does not undermine saying נותן טעם לפגם. nosen
ta’am lifgam. Even if it's true that the spices are off, אלא
השתא מיהא פגמא. ela hashta mei’ha pagma. It doesn't matter what it
would be in a theoretical circumstance that the spices would be better.
Right now there's a bad taste, so right now, so bottom line
is, the two versions are, just to say it outside because reading
inside is a little bit confusing me. But anyway, the two versions
are, according to one version, it says that as long as you
can attribute the פגם pgam to some other spices, you don't get
to say נותן טעם לפגם. nosen ta’am lifgam. Or the way תוספות
Tosfot says it, as long as you can sort of say the
only reason it's sort of, you know, in a theoretical case it
wouldn't be נותן טעם לפגם, nosen ta’am lifgam, it's only טעם לפגם
ta'am lifgam. because of this circumstance, so that's true, that you can
attribute it to the spices or there's or had the spices been
good, it would've been a would've been a good taste, then you
don't get to say נותן טעם לפגם. nosen ta’am lifgam. You only
get to say נותן טעם לפגם, nosen ta’am lifgam, this is the
the only
this is the מחמיר machmir position. The only time you get to
say נותן טעם לפגם nosen ta’am lifgam is if it can't be
attributed to anything else and if, you know, and if even in
a perfect case of the spices it still would have been פגם.
pgam. That's the narrow reading. The broader reading is you don't worry
about hypotheticals of what could have been or maybe it's something else,
you just say look, right now I know that there's an off-putting
taste and therefore I'm going to therefore assume and it doesn't matter
what in theory this pot could have been, right now this contributed
an off-put. And which one do we go by? We hold by
the latter one. So let's just read that, okay. So אמר רב
אמי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rav Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan, אמר רבי
אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Abahu amar Rabbi Yochanan, עד כדי
ad k'dei we're going to get to the fact that we פוסקן
pasken like the latter one in a minute, but just to tell
you, that's the bottom way we פוסקן. pasken. Don't worry about these
theoretical and hypotheticals. The reality is that the stuff gets added, it
makes the taste off-putting, it's going to be okay. Now do you
want to say something about the phrase of of אינה נאכלת מפני
זה? einah ne'echelet mipnei zeh? It's not eaten because of this. So
רש"י Rashi immediately says that's לאו דוקא. lav davka. As you know,
right, why do we allow cooking in a טריף treif בדיעבד bedi'avad
if you cooked in a טריף treif כלי, keli, you know, and
it's a day later we say the food is okay. Why? Because
we say after 24 hours it's נותן טעם לפגם. nosen ta'am lifgam.
I'd like a show of hands of anybody who's ever had this
happen and cooked in a טריף treif כלי keli a day later
and and made the food inedible. Obviously it does not make the
food inedible. Obviously these cases of נותן טעם לפגם nosen ta'am lifgam
the food doesn't have to be inedible, it just has to be
not as good not as good as it was. So so
רש"י Rashi says even though the language is אינה נאכלת מפני זה
einah ne'echelet mipnei zeh means that it makes it less desirable to
be eaten, not that it's inedible. I say that though because as
we're going to see when we get to tomorrow's דף, daf, we'll
see if we get to it today, anyway, the one of the
the basis of נותן טעם לפגם, nosen ta'am lifgam, the paradigm from
which we learn נותן טעם לפגם nosen ta'am lifgam is a case
where the thing is inedible. And that actually leads some ראשונים Rishonim
to try to explain that the scenarios in the גמרא Gemara of
נותן טעם לפגם, nosen ta'am lifgam, the thing really is inedible. Of
course it doesn't work, right, clearly these cases a little vinegar on
grits or whatever and certainly the case of כלים, keilim, the stuff
is not inedible. But the the basis for it is both the
source we're going to get to in a minute about the נבילה,
neveilah, an animal corpse, which is the source of it, and in
that case it really was inedible, and the language here of אינה
נאכלת מפני זה. einah ne'echelet mipnei zeh. So let me just tell
you the רא"ה's Ra'ah brilliant way of combining the two. The רא"ה
Ra'ah says the following, he says if, excuse me,
he says if the food is off-putting, let's say you had a
little bit of חזיר chazir that went into into your I don't
know cake or whatever, okay, and now it tastes a little bit
worse, okay. So he says if the food now tastes worse, that's
evidence of the fact that were you to be able to extract
the חזיר chazir taste by itself, it would be inedible. So the
חזיר chazir taste becomes, meaning it would be edible, inedible. He's going
with the idea that it has to be אינה נאכלת. einah ne'echelet.
The food is נאכלת ne'echelet because this is only a trace amount.
So if the food is נפגם nifgam a little, that's evidence that
the חזיר chazir taste is אינה נאכלת לגמרי. einah ne'echelet legamrei. Obviously
there's no logical connection between those. But anyway, I did want to
put it out there that obviously the פסק הלכה psak halacha is
is that it just has to be off-putting, it has to be
a little bit negative taste, but the language in the גמרא Gemara
here and and the case we're going to get to by נבילה
neveilah gives some ראשונים Rishonim פתח petach to think that maybe it
has to be the whole thing has to be inedible. Yeah. I
thought I'd clarify, but it's not your responsibility to then, in other
words you could fix it. What? Like you could have fixed it
like oh well, you know, with the way it is here if
I just add a little bit of sugar it would be perfectly
fine. No, doesn't matter. No, once it's נפגם nifgam and פגמו ולבסוף
השביח pagamu u'l'vasof hishbiach is fine. Once it enters in and it's
נפגם, nifgam, well then then it's sort of its end, it's בטל,
batel, end of story, okay. Actually I should I should bracket that.
נפגם ולבסוף השביח nifgam u'l'vasof hishbiach is somewhat of a quest. But
anyway, but you certainly... That's exactly what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
saying. You don't have to worry about hypotheticals. Right now it's פגום.
pagum. Well, first of all for ששים shishim you might have to
worry about that. Well, the whole point of ששים shishim is you
do have to worry about that. Okay, now we get to another
huge line here that's a little bit digression of נותן טעם לפגם,
note'n ta'am lifgam, but not really because it steps back and talks
about the general principle of טעם כעיקר ta'am k'ikar and there are
a few sort of brief little כלל klal lines that parallel this
statement we're about to read that where the whole discussion of what
is the halachic problem of טעם ta'am gets debated in the ראשונים,
rishonim, which is why you see this huge תוספות. Tosfos. So let's
read this line. אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan כל שטעמו וממשו kol sheta'amo umamasho anytime you have
the taste of something and its essence, and I'm going to get
back and explain that word essence, אסור assur it is forbidden ולוקין
עליו v'lokein alav and actually you get lashes if you had חזיר
chazir mixed up in your stew and it was not just the
taste of חזיר chazir but the essence of חזיר, chazir, and I'm
going to get back to what that word essence means, and then
you would actually get lashes for eating חזיר. chazir. וזהו כזית בכדי
אכילת פרס. V'zehu k'zayit b'khdei akhilat pras. And that would be in
a case where there was enough חזיר chazir in the stew that
you ate a כזית k'zayit of חזיר chazir in the time it
takes to eat a half a loaf of bread. How big is
a half a loaf of bread? Debate of רש"י Rashi and רמב"ם,
Rambam, one says it's eight כזיתים k'zeisim and one says it's nine
כזיתים. k'zeisim. So what that basically means is if you get חזיר
chazir mixed up in your stew in a one to eight or
one to nine proportion, so now once you eat nine כזיתים k'zeisim
of stew or eight כזיתים k'zeisim of stew, you've eaten one כזית
k'zayit of חזיר chazir and you've eaten that one כזית k'zayit in
that like you didn't watch it eating the soup slowly, you were
eating it constantly, so you ate that in the time it takes
to eat a פרס. pras. So then you have eaten a כזית
k'zayit of חזיר chazir in the time it takes to eat a
פרס, pras, that's the normal time period in הלכה halacha where all
is considered to be one act of eating, you've eaten a כזית
k'zayit in one act of eating and now we're going to give
you lashes. Even in that proportion you don't eat an actual כזית
k'zayit of חזיר, chazir, is that what you're saying? No, you need
a כזית k'zayit of חזיר. chazir. You will only get lashes if
you ingested a כזית k'zayit of חזיר. chazir. And you'll only get
lashes if you ingested that כזית k'zayit of חזיר chazir during the
time it takes to eat a פרס. pras. So it would be
physically impossible if it were in a proportion greater than one to
eight, one to nine. If it's in a proportion of one to
four and it took you twice as long as normal to eat
it, you'd also get lashes. Right? Okay. But if you have חזיר
chazir in your soup, it's mixed up, it's not only the taste,
it's the essence, then it's like you ate חזיר chazir we'll give
you lashes if you ate a כזית k'zayit in the sufficient amount
of time, in the minimum amount of time. Turn the page. טעמו
ולא ממשו, ta'amo v'lo mamasho, if it is the taste of חזיר
chazir but not the essence of חזיר, chazir, then אסור ואין לוקין
עליו, assur v'ein lokin alav, then it is forbidden but you don't
get
lashes. Okay? ואם ריבה טעם לפגם מותר, v'im riba ta'am lifgam mutar,
but if it increased the taste that now the taste is off-putting,
it is forbidden, it is permissible, that's טעם לפגם. ta'am lifgam So
that's obviously the connection here. So let's just wrap up the טעם
לפגם tam lifgam, then I'm going to go back and explain the
earlier line. ולימא אם נתן טעם לפגם מותר v'leima im natan ta'am
lifgam mutar why say ריבה? riba? Why didn't you say נתן? natan?
Just if it gave an off-putting taste it's permissible. הא קמשמע לן
דאף אגב דאיכא מילי אחרינייתא דפגמא בהדי haka mashma lan d'af agav
d'ika milei achrinaysa d'pogma bahadei even though there are other things that
contribute to the off-putting taste like the salt or the spices or
whatever, if this increased the off-putting taste, it wasn't the only source
of it, but it was an additional source, like the case that
the spices are off, nevertheless it's permissible. והלכתא כלישנא בתרא דריש לקיש.
v'hilchata k'lishna batra d'Reish Lakish. Mike is very happy, we actually פסקן.
pasken. Okay, so the הלכה halacha is like the last language, it
doesn't have to, you don't talk about theoretically had the spices been
different, as long as in the current scenario it added off-putting taste
it's permissible. Now let's, what is the difference between טעמו וממשו ta'amo
umamasho and טעמו ולא ממשו? ta'amo v'lo mamasho? So רש"י Rashi says
it's a physical difference. Okay. טעמו וממשו ta'amo umamasho would be a
case where the thing itself
basically, let's say you had a case of I don't know חזיר
chazir soup that you know like dissolved חזיר chazir that fell into
chicken soup. That would be ממשו mamasho because it's all the same,
it's like liquid and liquid. Or a piece of חזיר chazir that
fell into
your טשולנט cholent and you can't identify where the piece of חזיר
chazir is, okay? That would be ממשו mamasho because it's considered to
be like it's the thing itself. But says רש"י, Rashi, let's say
you basically you were doing a steak and a drop of חזיר
chazir soup or whatever dissolved חזיר chazir fell on your steak. That
would be טעמו ולא ממשו. ta'amo v'lo mamasho. Why? Because it's a
liquid that's being absorbed into a solid. It is considered in that
case that you only have the taste of the thing and not
the thing itself. The thing itself is the hard solid of the
steak and you have some חזיר chazir taste that got in here,
okay? So רש"י Rashi without figuring out exactly where to draw the
line, רש"י Rashi says the difference is a physical one. And for
רש"י, Rashi, okay, the idea right whenever people have learned you know
כשרות kashrus learned this principle of טעם כעיקר. ta'am k'ikar. The taste
is like the thing itself. So what רש"י Rashi says is that
that the debate, is the taste like the thing itself? was actually
debated in the גמרא, Gemara, is that a תורה Torah principle or
not, is in the case of טעמו ולא ממשו, taamo v'lo mamasho,
something like this, like a drop of חזיר chazer of חזיר chazer
soup being absorbed into a steak. But when you have טעמו וממשו,
taamo u-mamasho, let's, I'll give you a simpler example. You're making hamburger
and you take some חזיר chazer and you add in a little
חזיר chazer and you grind it all up with the beef. Okay,
רש"י Rashi says that's not a טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar question. That's
a question of the thing itself, it's all, it's mixed up. Okay,
you've got, you know, you got ground חזיר chazer and ground beef
and it's all mixed up. That's ממשו. mamasho. Everybody agrees that טעמו
וממשו, taamo u-mamasho, everybody agrees that that's דאורייתא. d'oraisa. That's not בטל.
battel. You get lashes for חזיר chazer כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. k'zayis
bichdei achilas pras. But טעמו וממשו taamo u-mamasho is like a drop
of the חזיר chazer soup that gets absorbed into the hamburger meat.
And that's the issue of טעם כעיקר. taam ke-ikkar. And therefore רש"י
Rashi says since the גמרא Gemara concludes אין לוקין עליו, ein lokin
alav, you don't get lashes, רש"י Rashi says the conclusion of this
גמרא Gemara is טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar is לאו דאורייתא. lav d'oraisa.
That טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar is not a biblical principle. So all
the concerns of all your pots and all that type of stuff
or whatever, we'll get to pots in a minute, that is only
a rabbinic concern that is not a biblical concern. טעם כעיקר taam
ke-ikkar is not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. It's only a problem when you have
the essence of the thing itself, okay, like hamburger, ground hamburger mixed
up with ground חזיר. chazer. Okay, that's רש"י. Rashi. תוספות, Tosafos, where'd
he say this?
Well, here he doesn't spell it out here. He says, anyway, תוספות
Tosafos has a long explanation where he quotes רש"י Rashi and spells
it out at the beginning of the תוספות Tosafos on רבי יוחנן.
Rabi Yochanan. It's other רש"יs Rashi as well, okay, there's like, these
are, there are a lot of סוגיות, sugyas, okay, this is a
composite position. Now, תוספות Tosafos says there, there's another more interesting read
which is a variation of רש"י Rashi without getting to describing the
difference between ממשו mamasho and not ממשו, mamasho, which is the following
discussion. Even if טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, that doesn't
necessarily mean you get lashes. Let's say you say טעם taam of
חזיר chazer is like חזיר. chazer. What is the word, what is
the meaning of that word 'is like', the letter כ, kaf, טעם
taam is כעיקר. ke-ikkar. Does it mean that it's really חזיר chazer
and you'll get lashes for eating it? Or does it mean, no,
it's אסור, assur, the same way חזיר chazer is אסור, assur, the
תורה Torah אסור-ed assur the טעם taam of חזיר, chazer, but it's
a different type of an איסור. issur. It's an איסור issur learned
from a different פסוק, pasuk, it's a more generic איסור. issur. Okay,
it's like when you say, you know, so therefore, what if it's
synthetically bacon? Okay, I'm not talking about that, that is a totally
different, when we say טעם taam it doesn't mean that if you
could replicate the טעם, taam, it means טעם taam that derives from
the actual physical thing itself. Okay, but anyway, this approach would say,
just because the גמרא Gemara says you don't get lashes, doesn't mean
it's not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. The reason you might get lashes, might be
that it is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but it's a different איסור. issur. It's
not חזיר, chazer, it's the טעם taam of חזיר chazer and that's
a different איסור, issur, so you don't get lashes. A third possibility
is it's דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but you know why you don't get lashes?
Because maybe the point of the גמרא Gemara is that the difference
of ממשו mamasho and not ממשו mamasho is not a physical difference,
but it's the proportions. When it's כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, k'zayis bichdei
achilas pras, then you're getting lashes because you ate a כזית k'zayis
worth. And טעמו ולא ממשו, taamo v'lo mamasho, you're not getting lashes
because you didn't eat a כזית k'zayis worth, is a scenario where
it's less than כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. k'zayis bichdei achilas pras. Okay,
so there's a lot of different ways of reading this גמרא Gemara
and what is the line between them. For example, רמב"ם Rambam says
טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar is דאורייתא d'oraisa when it's the proportions of
כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. k'zayis bichdei achilas pras. When it's not those
proportions, it's דרבנן. derabbanan. So anyway, a lot of different ways of
reading it, but just to quickly review. רש"י Rashi says the difference
is a physical difference of what is the type of way in
which the things are mixed and what's the, what's the physical reality
of the איסור issur compared to that of the היתר, heter, and
that he says the conclusion of this גמרא Gemara is that ממשו
mamasho is obviously דאורייתא, d'oraisa, that's like the hamburger case. טעם taam
is not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But other ways of reading it is that
טעם taam is דאורייתא d'oraisa but it's not the same איסור, issur,
or טעם taam is דאורייתא d'oraisa but you didn't eat enough to
be חייב, chayav, or you know, that טעם כעיקר taam ke-ikkar is
דאורייתא d'oraisa only when it's כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, k'zayis bichdei achilas
pras, it's sort of how רמב"ם Rambam reads it. Okay, it's anyway,
but how to parse this and how to parse what is טעם
taam and what is ממשו, mamasho, okay, is a big debate in
the ראשונים Rishonim and a big debate whether because we say טעם
כעיקר taam ke-ikkar is דאורייתא d'oraisa or not. Yes, Charlie. So this
idea that because you didn't eat enough, I mean that would go
along with what we say חצי שיעור אסור מן התורה chatzi shiur
assur min ha-Torah but you don't get lashes. Exactly. But isn't that
רבי יוחנן's Rabi Yochanan position? Yeah, we פסקן pasken that way. Yeah,
this is רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan also, by the way. So it
is, does fit with רבי יוחנן's Rabi Yochanan position of חצי שיעור.
chatzi shiur. So that is a way of reading the second part
of טעמו ולא ממשו. taamo v'lo mamasho. Okay, now let's continue. אמר
רב כהנא Amar Rav Kahana מתיבי כולם נאמר mitivi kulam ne'emar from
everybody we said until now, רבי יוחנן's Rabi Yochanan statement, ריש לקיש's
Reish Lakish statement, all these statements, והכי הלכתא vehachi hilchasa of the
משנה Mishna of טעם לפגם, taam lifgam from all of them they
all agree, נותן טעם לפגם מותר nosen taam lifgam mutar that טעם
לפגם ta'am l'fgam is permissible. אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. אביי
*Abaye* said in בשלמא מכולהו לחיי *bishlama mikulhu lachay* all the other
statements we said I agree with you, אלא דריש לקיש *ella dReish
Lakish* when ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* was explaining the position, ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish* said אמרו כמה *amru kama*, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* said
נותן טעם לפגם שאמרו Noten ta'am lifgam she'amru, לא שיאמר קדירה זו
*nosein tam lipgam sheamru lo sheyomar kedeira zo*, so he was sort
of explaining, explicating the position of those who held it, okay, וליה
לא סבירא ליה *vlei lo sevira lei* there's not clear that he
personally held of that position. Okay, anyway, but nevertheless the upshot is
נותן טעם לפגם nosein taam l'fgam מותר mutar. *nosein tam lipgam mutar*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מכלל דאיכא למאן דאמר נותן טעם
לפגם nosein taam l'fgam. אסור assur. *michlal deika leman damar nosein tam
lipgam assur*, we understood him to say that there's anybody who would
say that bad taste is forbidden? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אין *in*, yes! דתניא detanya, *detanya*, we taught in a ברייתא Baraita,
*braisa*, אחד נותן טעם לפגם ta'am l'fgam? ואחד נותן טעם ta'am לשבח
אסור assur, דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *echad nosein tam lipgam veechad
nosein tam leshevach assur divrei Rabbi Meir*. There you go. It was
an obvious softball question, okay, allowed us to introduce this ברייתא braisa
*braisa*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says that positive taste actually
is, I'm sorry, negative taste actually is forbidden, just like positive taste.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, אומר לשבח אסור assur ולפגם מותר mutar *Rabbi
Shimon omer leshevach assur ulifgam mutar*. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi
Shimon* is the one who we פסקן *pasken* like. He says that
bad taste is okay. You don't usually do that, right? פסקן *Pasken*
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* against רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir*. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? דרבי מאיר *Mai tama dRabbi Meir*
now, now we get to the source of all of this stuff.
What's the reason of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*? גמר מגעולי
עובדי כוכבים *Gamar migiulei ovdei kochavim*. He learns it out from געולי
*giulei*, געולי *giulei*'s like the, like this disgusting taste which means טעם
לפגם ta'am l'fgam *tam lipgam* of the vessels of non-Jews. Now that
doesn't mean like, it's not like a negative statement about non-Jews, but
anyway, it, maybe it is. What? Is it from הגעלה *hagalah*? It's
another word הגעלה *hagalah*, it's to purge, to expunge. Oh, that's what
it means, it's like the, I thought it was like לא תגעל
נפשי אתכם *lo sigal nafshi eschem* because that's why it's טעם לפגם
ta'am lifgam, *tam lipgam*. How does it translate that word Charlie over
there? Purging. Purging, expunge, right. Huh. That's what it is. It's not,
you mean, you mean the cooking together? Maybe. Oh, that's so interesting.
I always assumed it meant the פגם pagam, *pgam* taste that comes
from their כלים *keilim*. Maybe, okay. מגעולי עובדי כוכבים *Migiulei ovdei kochavim*.
Now, yeah, I guess so. I hear your point. Okay. Now which
basically means when the תורה Torah *Torah* said that you had to,
they took all those vessels from the Midianites and the תורה Torah
*Torah* said pass it through the fire, pass it through hot water.
Now the פשט *pshat* of those פסוקים *pesukim* is talking about a
type of a way of טהרה *taharah*, of טומאה וטהרה *tumah vetaharah*.
Of course it's funny, since when do you have טהרה *taharah* by
fire? So therefore חז"ל *Chazal* learn that the פשט *pshat* of those
פסוקים *pesukim* is that it's a way of כשר'ן *kashering* the vessels
that they took from the Midianites. So if you have to כשר
*kasher* it, it means that there would be a problem from the
תורה *Torah* using the vessels. But why is that? Wouldn't the taste
be off-putting, the taste that's absorbed in the vessels? So if the
תורה *Torah* says it's forbidden, that obviously shows you that even an
off-putting taste is still forbidden. געולי עובדי כוכבים *Giulei ovdei kochavim*, so
the taste that's expunged or expelled from the vessels, לאו נותן טעם
לפגם ta'am lifgam הוא *lav nosein tam lipgam hu*? It's bad, it's
off-putting taste, ואסרה רחמנא *veasrah Rachmana*, and the תורה *Torah* said you
can't use those vessels. הכא נמי לא שנא *Hacha nami lo shena*,
so that's a general principle that off-putting taste is no good. ואידך
*Veidach*, now what would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon? *Rabbi Shimon* say back?
כדרב הונא בריה דרב חייא דאמר רב הונא בריה דרב חייא לא
אסרה תורה אלא קדירה בת יומא דלאו לפגמו הוא *KideRav Huna brei
dRav Chiya damar Rav Huna brei dRav Chiya lo asrah Torah ella
kedeira bas yoma delav lifgamo hu*. No, the תורה *Torah* only forbade
them using those vessels on the day itself that it was captured,
which one wonders why they have to go through all that effort
of cleansing it or whatever, just wait a day. But I guess
the תורה *Torah* wanted to teach us laws of כשר'ן כלים *kashering
keilim*. Anyway, and on the day itself that it was absorbed, the
taste isn't off-putting. And that's the only reason it was forbidden, okay,
but if it was a day later, the תורה *Torah* would not
have forbade it because off-putting taste is not a problem. ואידך *Veidach*,
what would רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* say back? קדירה בת
יומא נמי אי אפשר דלא פגמה פורתא *Kedeira bas yoma nami ee
efshar delo pagma purta*. No, even on the same day itself it's
a little off-putting, and therefore anyway in which the תורה *Torah* forbade
it is a proof that bad taste is okay. Now, okay, so
that's that issue. I should say and I'll say one sentence about
the issue of כלים *keilim* because I mentioned before, do they, is
טעם ta'am, כעיקר דאורייתא *tam keikar d'Oraisa* or not? So for example,
רמב"ם *Rambam* rules that טעם ta'am כעיקר *tam keikar* is not דאורייתא
*d'Oraisa* unless it's כזית בכדי אכילת פרס *kezayis bichdei achilas pras*, unless
it's a high proportion of the mixture like one-eighth. And he also
rules though, that the, it sounds like he rules that the איסור
*issur* of using a כלי בת יומא *kli bas yoma* is דאורייתא
*d'Oraisa*. How do you reconcile those twos? So there is a גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that basically says, look, maybe כלים *keilim* is a חידוש
chiddush *chiddush*, meaning who, it's maybe it's not based on the principle
of טעם ta'am *tam*. Maybe טעם tam כעיקר *tam keikar* is not
דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*, but nevertheless if you cooked חזיר chazer *chazir* in this
pot, it becomes a חזיר chazer *chazir* pot, and the תורה *Torah*
doesn't want us to cook in it. So there's a question of
לכתחילה *lechatchila* letting us cook in it, which could be a separate
issue from how the תורה *Torah* treats טעם tam *tam* in general.
Okay, but the, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* everybody gets the point?
Like the fact that the תורה *Torah* says don't use a חזיר
chazer *chazir* pot isn't a proof that the תורה *Torah* treats the
טעם tam *tam* of חזיר chazer *chazir* as being a problem. Okay,
but nevertheless this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that they are intimately linked.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says if the תורה *Torah*
forbids us to use those pots even when it's a bad taste,
it shows that bad taste is a problem. And רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says back, I don't think the תורה *Torah*'s case
was when it was a bad or an off-putting taste. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, מאי טעמא
*Rabbi Shimon mai tama*? So now we understand where רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* gets his idea that it's אסור assur *assur*. Where
does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* get his idea that it's
מותר mutar, *mutar*? So the גמרא Gemara says the following. Hold on.
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon מאי טעמא? דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא,
braitah לא תאכלו כל נבלה, lo tokhlu kol neveilah, לגר אשר בשעריך.
lager asher b'sha'arekha. Don't eat any carcass of an animal, give it
to the stranger in your gates. כל הראוי לגר קרוי נבלה, kol
haraui lager kriya neveilah, only if it's fit for the stranger, meaning
if it's edible by human consumption, is it called a נבלה. neveilah.
שאינו ראוי לגר אינו קרוי נבלה. she'eina raui lager eina kriya neveilah.
If it's not edible, it's not a נבלה. neveilah. And this טעם
tam is not what? Edible? But it is edible. So that's the
whole problem I mentioned before. And that goes to the language of
אינה נאכלת. eina ne'echeles. But as we said before, the taste is
edible, it's just off-putting. So I'll get back to that in a
minute, but that's his principle. There we learn the idea that טעם
לפגם ta'am lifgam, is permissible. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir what would רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir say? He would say ההוא למעוטי סרוחה מעיקרא. hahu
l'motei srukha me'ikara. That's coming to—no, the case of a נבלה neveilah
that's permissible is if the moment it died it was inedible, like
it was already disease-ridden in life and the moment it died it
was inedible. But once it started as edible and therefore if it's
not ראוי raui to eat it at all, it's מותר. mutar, If
it never started life as ראוי raui to eat. If you eat
a נבלה neveilah if it was not—what are you saying? Or מותר
mutar. to give to the—like what does that mean? Meaning I could
eat a נבלה neveilah if it was never—well, that's also what רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying this
animal dies and then the meat becomes inedible, it becomes permissible to
eat. Okay? It has to be ראוי לגר. raui lager. And from
there we learn that a taste that becomes inedible is permissible to
be eaten or becomes bad is permissible to be eaten. רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says the only time the dead נבלה neveilah that's inedible
is permissible to be eaten is if it was inedible from the
moment it died. Okay? Then it never was defined as אסור. assur
But if from the—if it started when it died it was edible
and then it became inedible, since it started its status as אסור,
assur that status doesn't leave it. But why would you eat it?
If it was like alive and like—no, no, no, no, no. That
means it's not going to survive. Let's say it's just, I don't
know, it's got some disease that's eating it, it's not fatal and
the moment—nobody would eat it even from the second it died. You'd
eat that? נבלה? neveilah? Same, I mean, why are you more surprised
by that than רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says
even if it died and it was edible—but you still give it
to the גר ger or something but—no, שאינו ראוי לגר אינו קרוי
נבלה. she'eina raui lager eina kriya neveilah. Once it's inedible, it's not
a נבלה. neveilah. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir agrees to that principle. He
just says that would only be if it started life inedible. This
is a general halakhic principle which I call the stickiness principle, which
is that once something gets a halakhic status, you need a higher
threshold for it to lose it than if it never had that
status to begin with. Okay? Once you hire someone, it's a lot
harder to fire them than if you never hired them in the
first place. Okay,
so that's what רבי—so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if it started
off as edible, then it remains אסור assur. even if it becomes
inedible. רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir ההוא למעוטי סרוחה מעיקרא. hahu l'motei srukha
me'ikara. But the only time the תורה permits it is when it
was never edible. רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon רבי שמעון would say back,
סרוחה מעיקרא לא צריכה מיעוטא. srukha me'ikara lo tzerikha mi'uta. You wouldn't
even have needed a פסוק pasuk to tell you that. עפרא בעלמא
הוא. afra b'alma hu. That's just dirt. That's not even food. That's
not even called a נבלה. neveilah. The חידוש of the תורה is
even if it started as edible and became inedible, now it becomes
permissible. Now here's my question, which all the ראשונים Rishonim ask, it's
not my question, it's a question anybody would ask. What the heck
does an inedible נבלה neveilah have to do with טעם לפגם? ta'am
lifgam, טעם לפגם is just slightly off-putting. So as I said, it
leads some ראשון, Rishon, the ראב"ד Ra'avad or whatever, to try to
jump through hoops and to try to explain all the cases in
the גמרא Gemara that the food is inedible. You can't really do
that. So then it leads to another creative explanation by the ר"ה
Ra'ah to say that okay, the food is edible, but if the
taste is off-putting, it's evidence that the טעם, were you to be
able to extract it, it would be inedible. Which is a little
bit crazy, go ahead and take some חזיר chazer thing and mix
it into my, I don't know, strawberries. It's going to be off-putting
even though the חזיר chazir taste by itself might be very good,
right? So I don't know, maybe some people like bacon and strawberries.
Okay, so the general consensus is you're right. The food is edible,
the טעם by itself is edible, but here it's an analogy. Remember
how when we did our SATs we did these analogies, right? A
is to B as whatever. So here's the analogy. Okay, here the
analogy. נבלה neveilah meat is to inedible as נבלה neveilah טעם is
to like bad a taste. Why? Because inedible doesn't mean like physically
inedible, right? It's not like it's impossible, I would gag. Okay? Inedible
really means bad tasting. Right. Well, not bad tasting, right? No one
wants to eat it. So this is food is to something
that no one wants to eat as taste is to something that
no one wants to taste. Okay, so that basically by analogy for
food to become מותר, mutter, if you're dealing with an object of
food, it has to turn into something that no normal person wants
to eat. When you're dealing with the taste of נבילה nevelah that's
mixed into my stew, or that's mixed into my strawberries, or whatever
it might be, as taste, if it's a taste that nobody wants
to taste, that's not the טעם that the Torah forbade. When the
Torah says טעם is a problem, that only means good taste as
a problem. Okay, every time I say this I think about that
Starkist ad, when I said this to my students they had no
idea what I was talking about, but I grew up on this.
Everybody remember? Charlie, Starkist doesn't want tunas with good taste, Starkist wants
tunas that taste good. Okay, so anyway,
so taste, the same way the only food that is אסור assur
is food that is fit to be eaten, the only taste that
is אסור assur. is taste that is fit to be tasted, that
people want to taste, okay. So taste that you don't want to
taste is not the טעם that the Torah forbids. That is the
general way in which the ראשונים rishonim read this analogy. So just
let me try to understand something, so just with the נבילה nevelah
it's permissible you're saying, right, just wait a little while till it
gets bad, and then you can eat it. Yeah, but who wants
to eat stuff that nobody wants to eat? No, no, but then
with the טעם לפגם, maybe now it's okay, let me just wait
a little, then it'll be okay? Okay, so that's what the גמרא
Gemara is about to exactly discuss, is about this question of since
it seems that the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי
שמעון is about when it started good and now is bad, so
applying that to the טעם case, that should mean that when we
say טעם לפגם is okay, it's even if it started good and
became bad. But just a minute ago we said when it started
good and became bad it remains a problem. So that's exactly what
the גמרא Gemara, now is going to discuss. So let's read a
little further, get a little ahead. Okay, so the גמרא says like
this: אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, because this is exactly a follow-up to
what Michael said, מחלוקת שהשביח ולבסוף פגם. machlokes she-hishbiach u-levasof pagam. The
debate about רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי שמעון is when the
taste started good and became bad, just like that's their debate by
נבילה. nevelah. השביח hishbiach means it started good, it doesn't mean like
it got better. No, it made the food that it was added
to taste better, and now it made the food that it was
added to taste worse. ולבסוף פגם u-levasof pagam is to when it,
right, because that parallels their debate by נבילה. nevelah. אבל פגם מעיקרא
דברי הכל מותר, aval pagam me-ikara divrei hakol mutar, if it started
by adding a bad taste, everybody would agree that it's permissible, that's
paralleling the נבילה nevelah debate. איתיבי רב חגא לעולא, eisivei Rav Chaga
le-Ulla, so רב חגא Rav Chaga challenged עולא: Ulla: יין שנפל לתוך
עדשים וחומץ שנפל לתוך גריסין אסור רבי שמעון מתיר. yayin she-nafal le-toch
adashim ve-chometz she-nafal le-toch grisim assur Rabbi Shimon mattir. So when this
vinegar got mixed up to the grits it's forbidden, and here דפגם
מעיקרא הוא פליגי. de-pagam me-ikara hu pligi. This seems to be a
case where the taste started off as bad, and nevertheless רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir. says it's forbidden. אמר עולא חגא לא ידע מאי קאמרי
רבנן. Amar Ulla Chaga lo yada mai kamri rabbanan. חגא Chaga doesn't
even understand the ברייתא braitah he's reading. תיובתא קמותיב, tiyuvta kamosiv, he
has the חוצפה chutzpah to ask a question from it? הכא במאי
עסקינן שנפל לתוך גריסין צוננין והרתיחם. hacha be-mai askinan she-nafal le-toch grisim
tzonanin ve-hirticham. Who says, who told him that it started off tasting
bad? Now I don't know why he's so insulting of חגא, Chaga,
it was a reasonable read of the case, but anyway, I'm going
to say the case was, was that it started off by tasting
good, that it fell into cold grits, okay, and then you cooked
them up. נעשו כמו שהשביח ולבסוף פגם ואסור, na'asu ke-mo she-hishbiach u-levasof
pagam ve-assur, and that's the debate. So just the same way we
had that discussion earlier, I'm going to read their debate where it
started off good and it now became bad. That's עולא's Ulla position.
רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says:
בפוגם מעיקרא מחלוקת. be-pogem me-ikara machlokes. No, they debate only when it
started off bad. So the גמרא says איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, we
asked the question: בפוגם מעיקרא מחלוקת אבל השביח ולבסוף פגם דברי הכל
אסור. be-pogem me-ikara machlokes aval hishbiach u-levasof pagam divrei hakol assur. Would
he say that that's a debate but if it started off good
everybody would say it's forbidden, which was the sense one got at
the beginning of today's דף? daf? או דילמא בין בזו ובין בזו
מחלוקת, o dilma bein bazu u-vein bazu machlokes, that the one who
says it's permissible would say it's permissible in both cases, and the
one who says forbidden would say it's forbidden in both cases. So
the גמרא says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Now I'll say one
sentence about what Michael wants to ask, which is, how can we
say they're debating the case of פוגם מעיקרא? pogem me-ikara? Don't we
say by the נבילה nevelah that if it's פוגם מעיקרא, pogem me-ikara,
that if it tastes bad from the very beginning, רבי מאיר agrees
it's okay? So תוספות Tosfos says here's the difference, and it gets
a little bit to this whole discussion a minute ago. The נבילה,
nevelah, when it began its life as אסור assur, food, began as
permissible if it was פוגם מעיקרא. pogem me-ikara. This חזיר taste, this
חזיר stew, began its life as אסור. assur. It already is אסור
assur. as חזיר stew. When we say פוגם מעיקרא pogem me-ikara it
only means in its presence in the mixture, if from the very
outset the mixture was bad tasting. But just because you allow a
נבילה nevelah that was never edible to be מותר, mutter, it's not
the same, right? Here you've got your dead animal, okay, I don't
know how to make it an animal and not a person, okay,
X's in the eyes, okay, it never was נבילה, nevelah, okay, that's
סרוחה מעיקרא. srucha me-ikara. What do you mean it was never נבילה?
nevelah? It never was an אסור נבילה, assur nevelah, it never was
אסור. assur As soon as it became a נבילה nevelah it was
מותר. mutter. And now this is אסור, assur, right? This starts its
life as אסור. assur. Okay. Then here comes your טשאלנט cholent and
a little drop of here goes into this. That is a case
of פגום, pagum, well I don't know if חזיר would make your
טשאלנט cholent taste bad, whatever it is. It's some type of a
sweet thing, קאמפאט, compote, okay? I don't know. Okay. Anyway, that's פגום
מעיקרא, pagum me'ikara, but in the mixture it started its life as
bad tasting. But it started as אסור חזיר. assur chazir. So תוספות
Tosafot says even if you say this is okay, doesn't mean פגום
מעיקרא pagum me'ikara is okay. Since this started as אסור חזיר, assur
chazir, it'll remain it even if in the mixture it began as
bad tasting. Exactly. Then that obviously is okay. All right, so this
is the debate when they're debating the case of טעם לפגם, and
when we say it's מותר, are we talking about only when it
started in the mixture as bad taste or even if the mixture
started good and became bad? And that's where ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
says. ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is more מחמיר, machmir, and ר' יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan says it's only they're debating only when, or not only,
but we're going to say only when it started bad. But everybody
would agree is what we're going to say. We have now תיקו,
teiku, but we're going to move to say that according to ר'
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan when it started good in the mixture and became
bad, like we said at the beginning of today's דף, daf, everybody
would agree that that would be אסור. assur. Okay, so let's just
read a little bit more. We'll get to the bottom of the
דף, daf, so we'll get a little ahead. אמר רב פפא אמרם,
Amar Rav Pappa Amram, said Rav Amram, אפשר איתא להא דרבי יוחנן
ולא תניא לה במתניתין? Efshar ita le-ha de-Rebbi Yochanan velo tanya lah
be-matnitin? Is it possible that ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is right that
they debate a case about פגום מעיקרא pagum me'ikara and it's never
and we wouldn't find anything like this in a משנה? mishna? נפק
דק ואשכח. Nafak dak ve-ashkach. He went and he investigated and he
found the following משנה mishna that supports ר' יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. תנן.
Tenan. שאור של חולין שנפל לתוך עיסה. Se'or shel chulin she-nafal le-toch
isa. Ah, so now in anticipation of פסח Pesach we're getting some
cases about dough. Okay, so you have some sourdough of חולין chulin
that fell into dough. ויש בו כדי להחמיץ, Ve-yesh bo kedei le-hachmitz,
and there's enough sourdough to cause it to ferment. והחמיצה, Ve-hechmitza, and
it caused it to ferment. ואחר כך נפל שאור של תרומה או
שאור של כלאי הכרם. Ve-achar kach nafal se'or shel trumah o se-or
shel kilay ha-kerem. Then afterwards fell some forbidden שאור, se'or, תרומה trumah
sourdough or כלאים kilayim sourdough. Okay. ויש בו כדי להחמיץ, Ve-yesh bo
kedei le-hachmitz, and that has enough to ferment. Now the thing is,
once you had the right amount of sourdough, any additional sourdough, any
additional fermenting is טעם לפגם, okay, makes it worse. You don't want
too much sourdough. All right? So this additional thing is פגום מעיקרא.
pagum me'ikara. Everybody get it? Because as soon as the bad sourdough,
the אסור assur. sourdough fell in, it already was doing a bad
stuff. Okay. ואחר כך נפל שאור של תרומה או שאור של כלאי
הכרם ויש בו כדי להחמיץ, Ve-achar kach nafal se'or shel trumah o
se'or shel kilay ha-kerem ve-yesh bo kedei le-hachmitz, אסור, assur. it's forbidden.
רבי שמעון מתיר, Rebbi Shimon mattir, and ר' שמעון Rebbi Shimon allows
it. It's exactly this debate. והכא דפגום מעיקרא הוא פליגי. Ve-hacha de-pagum
me'ikara hu paligi. It's פגום pagum from the very beginning, and still
the first תנא קמא, tanna kamma, ר' מאיר, Rebbi Meir, says it's
forbidden. So you see that they argue in a case of פגום
מעיקרא. pagum me'ikara. אמר רבי זירא Amar Rebbi Zeira no, שאני עיסה
הואיל וחמיה בקמי עיסה דחברה. Shani isa ho'il ve-chamiah be-kamei isa de-chaverah.
Maybe the reason ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir forbids there is not that
ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir in general would forbid by פגום מעיקרא, pagum
me'ikara, but he actually says too much sourdough is not necessarily פוגם,
pogem, because it makes the dough now, you know, into it might
make the dough less good as bread, but it makes the dough
better as a starter. So therefore when you get a sourdough mixing
up into dough, you can use this new mixture as an expanded
starter. What is sourdough? Is dough that's used to ferment others? Yes,
yes. So therefore it's also called a starter or a culture. So
therefore he says that the reason ר' מאיר Rebbi Meir forbids, ר'
מאיר Rebbi Meir might in general say פגום מעיקרא pagum me'ikara is
okay, but here he forbids because it's not only פוגם, pogem, it
actually makes the dough usable in a different type of a way.
Okay, so now the גמרא is going to say תא שמע, ta
shema, let's try again. שאור של תרומה ושל חולין שנפלו לתוך העיסה.
Se'or shel trumah ve-shel chulin she-naflu le-toch ha-isa. So let's say the
תרומה trumah and the חולין chulin fell at the same time, okay,
which is hard to therefore define it, whether the תרומה trumah one
is doing a bad job or a good job because the total
amount is too much, but they fell the same time, so you
don't know which one to blame it on. Okay? בזה כדי להחמיץ
ובזה כדי להחמיץ וחמצו, Be-zeh kedei le-hachmitz u-be-zeh kedei le-hachmitz ve-chimtzu, and
they made so each one was enough, together it was too much,
ואסור, ve-assur, it's forbidden, ורבי שמעון מתיר. ve-Rebbi Shimon mattir. So that's
not a good proof because it's not clear how you can conceptualize
that. נפל של תרומה תחילה, Nafal shel trumah techilah, now if the
תרומה trumah fell first, דברי הכל אסור, divrei ha-kol assur, everybody would
agree that's forbidden. So by the way that's a case of השביח
ולבסוף פגם. hishbiach u-le-vasof pagam. Right, the תרומה trumah fell in, made
it better, in the end the whole stuff tastes bad because too
much sourdough fell in, and that remains forbidden. So by the way
this is going to be a proof to ר' יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan.
Here it's השביח ולבסוף פגם hishbiach u-le-vasof pagam and everybody agrees. Everyone
agrees that it's forbidden. So this ברייתא really is a proof to
רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, makes it clear that they only debate פגם
מתחילה. pagam mitchilah. השביח לבסוף פגם hishbiach l'basof pagam everybody agrees is
forbidden. נפל של חולין ואחר כך נפל של תרומה nafal shel chullin
v'achar kach nafal shel terumah which was our case, או של כלאי
הכרם או של כלאי הכרם, o shel kilay hakerem o shel kilay
hakerem, אסור ורבי שמעון מתיר. assur v'Rebbi Shimon matir. Okay, which is
the case of השביח hishbiach which is the case of פגם מתחילה.
pagam mitchilah. Okay. So this ברייתא is basically going to say that
because of these three cases it's pretty clear that פגם מתחילה, pagam
mitchilah, that's their debate, when the תרומה, terumah, when the תרומה terumah
fell after when it was too when after the other sourdough was
there. So from the very outset the תרומה terumah added a bad
taste, that's their debate. But if the תרומה terumah fell first, everybody
agrees it remains אסור. assur, So פגם, so השביח לבסוף פגם hishbiach
l'basof pagam everybody agrees is אסור. assur. פגם ולבסוף השביח, pagam u'levasof
hishbiach, that's the debate. Excuse me. פגם מתחילה, pagam mitchilah, that's the
debate. Okay. השביח לבסוף פגם hishbiach l'basof pagam everybody agrees is אסור.
assur, So the גמרא says והכא דפגם מעיקרא ופליגי. v'hacha d'pagam mei'ikra
u'pligi. Here again when the תרומה terumah fell second, so from the
moment the תרומה terumah fell, fell in, it added a bad taste
and that's the debate. So that's proof to רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan.
Okay? וכי תימא הכא נמי כרבי זירא, v'chi teima hacha nami k'Rebbi
Zeira, let's say, oh, it's like רבי זירא. Rebbi Zeira. The only
reason רבי מאיר says it's forbidden is not that רבי מאיר really
has a problem with פגם מתחילה, pagam mitchilah, but that because it
is not, he says it's not פוגם pogem because it just makes
it better to use as sourdough. So תא שמע, ta shema, come
in here, מסיפא. m'seifa. היין שנפל לתוך עדשים וחומץ שנפל לתוך גריסין.
hayayin shenafal l'toch adashim v'chometz shenafal l'toch grisin. So fine. From the
earlier case about the sourdough that רבי מאיר said it's forbidden, you
can't prove it. Maybe it's a special issue about sourdough. But how
about this case? Wine that fell on these lentils and vinegar that
fell on the grits, אסור ורבי שמעון מתיר. assur v'Rebbi Shimon matir.
והכא נמי דפגם מעיקרא. v'hacha nami d'pagam mei'ikra. Again the simple reading
of this is that it is tasting bad from the very outset
ופליגי. u'pligi. So again the simple reading of all of this is
that they are arguing on cases where it's bad tasting from the
outset. וכי תימא הכא נמי כדישני ליה עולא לרבי חגא השביח לבסוף
פגם. v'chi teima hacha nami k'dishani lei Ulla l'Rebbi Chaga hishbiach l'basof
pagam. Oh, maybe this is like עולא Ulla said. No, no, the
case was that initially it was cold and then it was heated
up and it wasn't bad tasting at the outset. ומי פליגי כשהשביח
לבסוף פגם? u'mi pligi k'shehishbiach l'basof pagam? But you can't say that
because to say that this case was that it started cold and
good and then it became bad would have רבי מאיר and רבי
שמעון arguing in a case of השביח לבסוף פגם. hishbiach l'basof pagam.
But from the case of the of the sourdough you see that
they agree that that's a problem. והקתני נפל של תרומה תחילה דברי
הכל אסור. v'hakatani nafal shel terumah techilah divrei hakol assur. Okay, so
it's getting a little confusing. But here are the cases. Okay, so
you have one case which is number one is תרומה terumah and
then stage number one and stage number two is, so here תרומה
terumah is already in it and then the חולין chullin goes in.
Okay. So that's a case which is which is a case of
השביח לבסוף פגם. hishbiach l'basof pagam. And the גמרא said in this
case דברי הכל אסור, divrei hakol assur, right, because initially the תרומה
terumah was good. Okay, the other, that's case number one. The other
case is first you had חולין chullin and then you had, so
here's the חולין chullin and then you had the תרומה terumah fall
in and then you had the תרומה. terumah. So when the תרומה
terumah fell in, what, what did the תרומה terumah do? Okay. So
in this case from the very moment the תרומה terumah fell in,
okay, it was bad. So that's a case of פגם מתחילה pagam
mitchilah and that the conclusion is is that is the מחלוקת. machlokes.
So that's a pretty good proof to רבי שמעון. In this case
השביח לבסוף פגם דברי הכל אסור. hishbiach l'basof pagam divrei hakol assur.
This case is where it's פגם מתחילה pagam mitchilah from the moment
the תרומה terumah fell in was פוגם pogem is the מחלוקת. machlokes.
Now you'll say one minute. Maybe the reason רבי מאיר forbids this
is because it's not really פוגם, pogem, it's because it actually makes
it better as yeast. Ah, says the גמרא, but we've got a
third case. The third case is the חומץ chometz that falls into
the גריסין. grisin. Okay, and we're going to assume that that's a
case of פגם מתחילה pagam mitchilah and still we're going to see
מחלוקת. machlokes. So you see פגם מתחילה pagam mitchilah is a מחלוקת
machlokes and השביח לבסוף פגם דברי הכל אסור. hishbiach l'basof pagam divrei
hakol assur. That's exactly a proof to רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. Now
you want to get out of this and say maybe it was
all cold and if it was all cold it was השביח לבסוף
פגם. hishbiach l'basof pagam. But you can't say that this is השביח
לבסוף פגם hishbiach l'basof pagam because here they debate and here השביח
לבסוף פגם hishbiach l'basof pagam they all agree is אסור. assur Okay.
So since here you see they are השביח לבסוף פגם hishbiach l'basof
pagam they all agree is אסור, we have to read this case
כפשוטו k'pishuto that it's פגם מתחילה pagam mitchilah and therefore it's a
מחלוקת machlokes and therefore the whole thing is a proof to רבי
יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. So let's just finish that. וכי תימא הכא נמי
כדישני ליה לרבי חגא כשהשפילה בסוף פגם? vechitaima hachanami kedeshani lei leRebbi
Chaga k'shehishpila besof pagam? You want to read this that it also
started off cold and was השפילה בסוף פגם? hishpila besof pagam? ומי
פליגי? umi pligi? But then they wouldn't be debating that כשהשפילה בסוף
פגם. keshehishpila besof pagam. הא ותני נפל של תרומה תחילה דברי הכל
אסור. ha vatni nafal shel teruma techila divrei hakol assur. Here's a
case of השפילה בסוף פגם hishpila besof pagam and everybody agrees it's
forbidden. So how, so therefore, the only way this could be a
מחלוקת machlokes is if this is a case of פגם מתחילה. pagam
mitechila. אלא לאו שמע מינא בפגם מעיקרא מחלוקת שמע מינא. ela lav
shema mina bepagam meikara machlokes shema mina. So you see they debate
פגם מתחילה pagam mitechila and this is not special because it's yeast
and sourdough, and they agree with השפילה בסוף פגם. hishpila besof pagam.
So actually, not only is it evidence for רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan,
but it also shows that the only place they debate is פגם
מתחילה. pagam mitechila. And that's why we started today's דף daf to
say if it's השביח ולבסוף פגם hishbiach ulebesof pagam it's אסור. So
נותן טעם לפגם yes is מותר, but only if it's פוגם מתחילה.
pogem mitechila. And that's a debate of רבי שמעון and רבי מאיר.
We rule like רבי שמעון that when it's פוגם מתחילה pogem mitechila
it's מותר. If it's השביח ולבסוף פוגם, hishbiach ulebesof pogem, once the
thing originally becomes אסור, it remains אסור and everybody agrees in that
case you cannot rely on נותן טעם לפגם. Okay, we'll end with
that.